<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transcription Factors on Ish</title>
    <link>https://ishwariyavenkatesh.github.io/tags/transcription-factors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Transcription Factors on Ish</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Ish Venkatesh</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ishwariyavenkatesh.github.io/tags/transcription-factors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Transciptional Control of Axon growth</title>
      <link>https://ishwariyavenkatesh.github.io/project/networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ishwariyavenkatesh.github.io/project/networks/</guid>
      <description>Axons are the cables in your nervous system that carry information from the brain to the rest of the body. Injured adult mammalian neurons in the central nervous system (CNS) fail to re-grow axons (Spinal cord injury), resulting in irreversible permanent damage. However, in nature, several types of neurons are intrinsically capable of robust axon regeneration following injury. These include early post-natal CNS neurons that then lose the capacity for re-growth in a developmental transition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenetic manipulation of axon growth</title>
      <link>https://ishwariyavenkatesh.github.io/project/accessibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ishwariyavenkatesh.github.io/project/accessibility/</guid>
      <description>Axons in the mammalian central nervous system possess low regenerative capacity, which limits functional recovery from spinal cord injury. In contrast to central nervous system (CNS) neurons, regeneration competent peripheral neurons precisely activate key genes in response to axonal injury, resulting in regenerative success. Improving the CNS cell body response to injury in order to enhance axon regeneration is thus a key research goal. In particular, forced expression of critical transcription factors, which can orchestrate the production of the many regeneration-associated proteins, is emerging as an effective way to improve the complex task of axon extension.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>